Guide to the Caldwell B. Esselstyn Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Principal Professional Activities, 1946-1974; Series II; 11' (27 boxes)
  - Programs and Projects
    - Publications and Photographs
      - Publications
        - Proceedings of the Rip Van Winkle Clinic, Volume XIII, 1-4, 1962 (Box 37, Folder 246)
        - Proceedings of the Rip Van Winkle Clinic, mailing lists, Circa 1960 (Box 38, Folder 247)
        - "The Wee Winkle," Volume II, 1955 (Box 38, Folder 248)
        - "The Wee Winkle," Volume III, 1956 (Box 38, Folder 249)
        - "The Wee Winkle," Volume IV, 1957 (Box 38, Folder 250)
        - "The Wee Winkle," Volume V, 1959 (Box 38, Folder 251)
        - "The Wee Winkle," Volumes VI-IX, 1960-1961 (Box 38, Folder 252)
      - Photographs
        - 14 prints [Benjamin M. Spock and others, meeting re: "Developing Comprehensive Rural Group Medical Practice," Hudson and Philmont (New York)], Circa 1956 July 2 (Box 38, Folder 253)
        - 34 prints of clinic buildings, undated (Box 38, Folder 254)
        - 18 prints of staff, patients, clinic interior, undated (Box 38, Folder 255)
        - 4 prints, C.B.E. with others, undated (Box 38, Folder 256)
    - Reference Material
      - Hudson and Columbia County
        - "Proceedings, Columbia County Conference on Youth", 1960 May 14 (Box 38, Folder 257)
        - Report, "Community Environmental Health Survey", Circa 1959 (Box 38, Folder 258)
        - Report, "Public Health Survey of the Medical Resources of Columbia County", 1955 (Box 38, Folder 259)
        - "Summary Report of the Columbia-Greene Rehabilitation Service", 1957 (Box 38, Folder 260)
        - Miscellaneous pamphlets, 1958-1962 (Box 38, Folder 261)
      - New York State
        - Publications re: children and youth, 1960 (Box 38, Folder 262)
        - "Statistical Report of Psychiatric Clinics in New York State", 1963 (Box 39, Folder 263)
      - R.V.W.F.
        - Newsclippings, 1946-1965 (Box 39, Folder 264-270)
        - Report, "Health Resources Survey - 1957" (Box 39, Folder 271)
        - Report, "The Rural Medical Problem", undated (Box 39, Folder 272)
        - Miscellaneous articles and reports, 1950, 1958, undated (Box 39, Folder 273)
  - Community Health Association
    - Background Material
      - Proceedings, Conference on Quality of Medical Care, 1957 January 11-12 (Box 39, Folder 274)
      - Revised proceedings, Conference on Quality of Medical Care, 1957 January 11-12 (Box 40, Folder 275)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1964-1967 September (Box 40, Folder 276-281)
      - General, 1967 October- 1968 (Box 40, Folder 282)
      - Select
        - American Medical Association (Box 40, Folder 282)
          See: box 11, folder 260
        - Bannon, Kenneth, 1965-1966 (Box 40, Folder 283)
        - Bushnell, George, 1964-1967 (Box 40, Folder 284)
        - Deitch, Daniel, 1957-1967 (Box 40, Folder 285)
        - Fein, Rashi (Box 40, Folder 285)
          See: box 13, folder 318
        - Glasser, Melvin, 1965-1966 February (Box 40, Folder 286)
        - Glasser, Melvin, 1966 March - 1967 (Box 40, Folder 287)
        - Group Health Association of America (Box 40, Folder 287)
          See: box 59, folder 103
        - Kaiser Foundation (Box 40, Folder 287)
          See box 14, folders 349-351
        - Mazey, Emil, 1964-1967 (Box 40, Folder 288)
        - Medical Foundation of Bellaire (Box 40, Folder 288)
        - Michigan, University of (Box 40, Folder 288)
          See: box 15, folder 382
        - Mott, Frederick (Box 40, Folder 288)
          See: box 16, folder 384
        - Nelson, John A. (Box 40, Folder 288)
          See: box 16, folder 392
        - Ravitz, Melvin (Box 40, Folder 288)
          See: box 17, folder 419
        - Reeves, Arthur (Box 40, Folder 288)
          See: box 13, folder 320
        - Reuther, Walter, 1964-1968 (Box 40, Folder 289)
        - Scholdager, Rolf (Box 40, Folder 289)
          See: box 17, folder 427
        - Stewart, William H. (Box 40, Folder 289)
        - Trese, John A. (Box 40, Folder 289)
          See: box 18, folder 439
        - United Auto Workers (Box 40, Folder 289)
          See: box 18, folders 442-447
        - United Steel Workers of America (Box 40, Folder 289)
          See: box 19, folder 464
        - Verhelle, Joseph, 1965-1966 (Box 41, Folder 290)
        - Zwerdling, Abraham, 1965-1971 (Box 41, Folder 291)
    - Administrative and Program Papers
      - Correspondence and reports re: legislation, 1958-1965 January (Box 41, Folder 292)
      - Correspondence, reports and notes re: operation of C.H.A., 1958-1971 (Box 41, Folder 293)
      - Statistical tables and reports re: service and enrollment, 1963-1964 (Box 41, Folder 294)
      - Correspondence, notes and reports re: Medical Institutes of Local 88, Meat and Related Industries Welfare Fund Trust, 1964-1965 (Box 41, Folder 295-296)
      - Correspondence and news releases re: Great Lakes Consumer Conference, 1964 (Box 41, Folder 297)
      - Correspondence, reports and newsletters re: Mental Health Program, 1964-1965 (Box 41, Folder 298)
      - Correspondence, minutes, speech and agreement re: Metropolitan Hospital, 1964-1971 (Box 41, Folder 299)
      - Correspondence and reports re: legislation, 1965 February - 1966 (Box 41, Folder 300)
      - Correspondence and reports re: project grants, 1965 (Box 41, Folder 301)
      - Correspondence and reports re: Workmen's Compensation, 1965 (Box 41, Folder 302)
      - Report, "Choice of Health Care Plans," University of Michigan School of Public Health, 1965 (Box 41, Folder 303)
      - Pamphlets, 1965-1966 (Box 42, Folder 304)
      - Correspondence, pamphlets and reports re: Home Health Care Project, 1965-1967 (Box 42, Folder 305)
      - Correspondence and news releases re: Lamaze Method of Childbirth, 1966 (Box 42, Folder 306)
      - Newsletters re: Michigan Blue Cross Medicare Bulletin, 1966 (Box 42, Folder 307)
      - Correspondence, reports and newsletters re: Mental Health Program, 1966-1967 (Box 42, Folder 308)
      - Newsletters re: Michigan Blue Cross Medicare Bulletin, 1967 (Box 42, Folder 309)
      - Report re: City of Detroit, Mayor's Committee for Human Resources Development, Comprehensive Neighborhood Health Center, 1967 (Box 42, Folder 310)
  - New York Metropolitan Regional Medical Program
    - General
      - Background material re: President's Commission on Heart:Disease, Cancer and Stroke, 1964-1968 (Box 42, Folder 311)
      - Correspondence, reports and notes, 1966 June - 1968 (Box 42, Folder 312-313)
      - Interoffice memoranda, 1967 (Box 43, Folder 314)
      - Correspondence re: Putnam County Medical Society, 1967-1968 (Box 43, Folder 315)
      - Correspondence and newsletters re: Regional Plan Association, Inc., 1967-1968 (Box 43, Folder 316)
      - Correspondence and print material re: conference-workshop on the operation of R.M.P.'s, 1967-1968 (Box 43, Folder 317)
      - Correspondence and print material re: Gouvernour Health Services proposal, 1967-1968 (Box 43, Folder 318)
      - Correspondence, memoranda and reports re: Memorial Hospital Feasibility Program, 1967-1968 (Box 43, Folder 319)
      - Correspondence, reports and newsletters re: operation of R.M.P.'s by National Institutes of Health, 1967-1968 (Box 43, Folder 320)
      - Monthly activities reports, 1967-1968 (Box 43, Folder 321)
      - Notes and reports re: Planning Conference, 1968 Sun 20 (Box 43, Folder 322)
      - Annual trustee report and revised guidelines, 1968 (Box 43, Folder 323)
      - Correspondence and print material re: mobile coronary care unit proposal, 1968 (Box 44, Folder 324)
      - Correspondence and print material re: Pediatric Pulmonary Disease Center project, 1968 (Box 44, Folder 325)
      - Correspondence and print material re: research and evaluation, 1968 (Box 44, Folder 326)
      - Interoffice memoranda, 1968 (Box 44, Folder 327)
      - Reports and newsletters re: News Information Data, 1968 (Box 44, Folder 328)
      - American Federation of Industrial Organizations, N.Y. City Central Labor Council (Box 44, Folder 328)
        See: box 11, folder 258
      - American Medical Association, Emergency Medical Services Committee (Box 44, Folder 328)
        See: box 11, folder 262
      - Association of American Medical Colleges (Box 44, Folder 328)
        See: box 11, folder 268
      - New York State Department of Health, Health Manpower Group (Box 44, Folder 328)
        See: box 17, folder 403
      - New York State Department of Health, Health Resources Commission (Box 44, Folder 328)
        See: box 17, folder 404
      - Segal, Martin E. (Box 44, Folder 328)
    - Committees and Councils
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Pulmonary Disease: minutes, 1968 (Box 44, Folder 329)
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Urban Problems: correspondence notes and reports, 1967 (Box 44, Folder 330)
      - Advisory Committee
        - Correspondence, minutes, notes and reports, 1967 June - 1968 March (Box 44, Folder 331-333)
        - Correspondence, minutes, notes and reports, 1968 April-August (Box 44, Folder 334)
      - Advisory Committee Annual Meeting: reports, notes and summaries, 1968 February 19 (Box 44, Folder 334)
      - Cancer Subcommittee: correspondence, memoranda and reports, 1967-1968 (Box 44, Folder 336)
      - Coordinator's Committee: correspondence, minutes, notes and reports, 1967-1968 (Box 44, Folder 337)
      - Dental Subcommittee: correspondence and reports, 1968 (Box 44, Folder 338)
      - Diabetes Subcommittee: memoranda and minutes, 1968 (Box 44, Folder 339)
      - Health Careers for the Disadvantaged Committee
        - Correspondence, reports and notes, 1967 December - 1968 January (Box 44, Folder 340-341)
        - Correspondence, reports and notes, 1968 February 1-19 (Box 45, Folder 342)
        - Correspondence and reports, 1968 February 20-29 (Box 45, Folder 343)
        - Correspondence, reports and notes, 1968 March-April (Box 45, Folder 344-345)
        - Correspondence and reports, 1968 May-July (Box 45, Folder 346)
        - Correspondence and notes re: fund raising, 1968 (Box 45, Folder 347)
        - Drafts of resolutions and related notes, 1968 (Box 45, Folder 348)
        - Notes, undated (Box 45, Folder 349)
      - Heart Disease Subcommittee: minutes and memoranda, 1968 (Box 45, Folder 350)
      - New York State Joint Council on R.M.P's: agenda, participant list and notes, 1967-1968 (Box 45, Folder 351)
      - Renal Subcommittee: correspondence, reports and print material, 1968 (Box 45, Folder 352)
      - Respiratory Disease Subcommittee: notes, memoranda and reports, 1968 (Box 45, Folder 353)
      - Steering Committee: minutes, memoranda and reports, 1968 (Box 45, Folder 354)
      - Subcommittee on Continuing Education: correspondence, notes and reports, 1968 (Box 45, Folder 355)
      - Subcommittee on Evaluation
        - Correspondence, notes and reports, 1967 April - 1968 (Box 46, Folder 356-358)
      - Subcommittee on Home Care: minutes, notes and reports, 1968 (Box 46, Folder 359)
      - Subcommittee on Home Health Agencies
        - Correspondence, reports and print material, 1967 (Box 46, Folder 360)
        - Correspondence, reports and notes, 1968 (Box 46, Folder 361)
      - Subcommittee on Stroke: minutes, notes and reports, 1968 (Box 46, Folder 362)
    - Other R.M.P.'s
      - Albany: correspondence, report and print material, 1967 (Box 46, Folder 363)
      - Central New York: grant application and minutes, 1967-1968 (Box 46, Folder 364)
      - Connecticut: correspondence and reports, 1965-1968 (Box 46, Folder 365)
      - Greater Delaware Valley: correspondence and reports, 1967-1968 (Box 46, Folder 366)
      - Maine: grant application and correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 46, Folder 367)
      - Michigan: correspondence and reports, 1967-1968 (Box 47, Folder 368)
      - Missouri: progress report, 1967 (Box 47, Folder 369)
      - New Jersey: reports, 1967-1968 (Box 47, Folder 370)
      - Pittsburgh: correspondence and reports, 1966-1967 (Box 47, Folder 371)
      - Rochester: program report and evaluation, 1966-1967 (Box 47, Folder 372)
      - South Carolina: grant application, 1967 (Box 47, Folder 373)
      - Western New York: grant application, 1967 (Box 47, Folder 374)
  - New York State Department of Health, Bureau of Emergency Medical Services
    - General correspondence, notes, news releases and reports re: job descriptions and appointment, 1968-1969 (Box 47, Folder 375)
    - Public Health Service report on E.M.S. and related correspondence, 1970 (Box 47, Folder 376)
    - Ambulatory Care Committee
      - Correspondence and reports, 1970 October- 1971 December (Box 47, Folder 377-380)
    - Committee on the Delivery of Health Services: correspondence and reports, 1971 (Box 48, Folder 381)
    - Physician's Assistant Program: correspondence and reports, 1972 (Box 48, Folder 382)
    - State Technical Advisory Committee on Emergency Health Services
      - Correspondence and reports, 1972 (Box 48, Folder 383)
      - Correspondence and reports, 1973-1974 (Box 48, Folder 384)
    - American Medical Association, Emergency Medical Services Committee (Box 48, Folder 384)
    - Ast, David (Box 48, Folder 384)
      See: box 11, folder 269
    - Hilleboe, Herman E. (Box 48, Folder 384)
      See: box 13, folder 338
    - Ingraham, Hollis (Box 48, Folder 384)
      See: box 14, folder 343
    - Larimore, Granville (Box 48, Folder 384)
      See: box 14, folder 359
    - New York State Employees Retirement System (Box 48, Folder 384)
      See: box 17, folder 406
  - United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, Health Maintenance Organization Service
    - General
      - Correspondence and reports, 1971-1972 Mar, 1972 May-1973 (Box 48, Folder 385-391)
      - Correspondence and reports, 1974 (Box 49, Folder 392)
      - Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York (Box 49, Folder 392)
        See: box 80, folder 295
      - New York State Bureau of Emergency Medical Services (Box 49, Folder 392)
        See: box 48, folder 383
      - Seubold, Frank (Box 49, Folder 392)
    - Subject Files
      - Print material, 1972 (Box 49, Folder 393)
      - Correspondence and reports re: H.M.O. seminar, 1972 October -1973 May (Box 49, Folder 394)
      - Correspondence, reports and clippings re: Professional Standards Review Organization, 1972-1973 (Box 49, Folder 395)
      - Correspondence and reports re: Task Group Five, 1973 January November 1 (Box 49, Folder 396)
      - Correspondence and reports re: Task Group Five, 1973 November 3-28 (Box 49, Folder 397)
      - Correspondence and reports re: Task Group Five, 1973 December 1-14 (Box 49, Folder 398)
      - Correspondence and reports re: Task Group Five, 1973 December 15 -1974 January (Box 49, Folder 399)
      - Program and participant list re: National Conference for Developing Title XIX-H.M.O. Contracts, 1973 (Box 49, Folder 400)
      - Correspondence and reports re: PLC-73-147 J.R. (C.B.E. report on quality care), 1973-1974 (Box 49, Folder 401)
      - Correspondence and reports re: quality assurance, 1973-1974 (Box 49, Folder 402)
      - Meeting minutes, 1974 (Box 49, Folder 403)
- Other Professional Activities, 1952-1973; Series III; 15' (37 boxes)
  OTHER PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES is organized in seven subsections: American Public Health Association, Group Health Association of America, Health Insurance Benefits Advisory Council, Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York, Inc., New York-State Public Health Council, Physicians Committee for Health Care for the Aged through Social Security, and Public Affairs Committee, Inc. The larger sections are organized in subsections.
  - American Public Health Association
    - General Papers
      - Correspondence and press releases, 1957-1958 (Box 50, Folder 1)
      - Technical Development Board: minutes, 1959 September-October (Box 50, Folder 2)
      - Executive Board: minutes, 1959 October (Box 50, Folder 3)
      - Governing Council and Executive Board: correspondence, minutes and resolutions, 1959-1961 (Box 50, Folder 4)
      - Minutes and memoranda, 1959-1961 (Box 50, Folder 5)
      - Governing Council: order of business, 1961 (Box 50, Folder 6)
      - Requests for fellowships and nominations for prizes, 1963-1964 (Box 50, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence, reports and memoranda, 1966-1973 (Box 50, Folder 8)
    - Committees and Sections
      - Committee on Administrative Practice, Subcommittee on Medical Care
        - Reprint, 1949 (Box 50, Folder 9)
        - Memoranda, 1952-1953 (Box 50, Folder 10)
        - Correspondence, agenda and reprints, 1954 (Box 50, Folder 11)
        - Minutes, reprints and legislation, 1955 (Box 50, Folder 12)
        - Correspondence and memoranda, 1956-1957 (Box 50, Folder 13)
        - "Voluntary Medical Care Insurance: An Evaluation of Present Plans and Future Potentials": drafts, 1957 (Box 50, Folder 14)
      - Long Range Planning Committee: correspondence, 1966 (Box 51, Folder 15)
      - Medical Care Section
        - Medical Care Section Newsletter, 1954-1968 (Box 51, Folder 16)
        - Amended constitution, correspondence and related material, 1959 (Box 51, Folder 17)
        - Correspondence, memoranda and related material, 1960 January-March (Box 51, Folder 18)
        - Correspondence, memoranda and related material, 1960 April-July (Box 51, Folder 19)
        - Correspondence, minutes and related material, 1960 August-September (Box 51, Folder 20)
        - Correspondence, minutes and related material, 1960 October-December (Box 51, Folder 21)
        - Membership kit, 1960 (Box 51, Folder 22)
        - Correspondence, directories and minutes, 1961 January-June (Box 52, Folder 23)
        - "Program Planning for 1961 Annual Meeting," manual, 1961 March 8 (Box 52, Folder 24)
        - Correspondence, resolutions and related material, 1961 July-December (Box 52, Folder 25)
        - Southern branch: correspondence and report, 1961 (Box 52, Folder 26)
        - Abstracts of contributed papers, A.P.H.A. meeting, 1961 (Box 52, Folder 27)
        - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 52, Folder 28)
        - Correspondence and related material, 1963 (Box 52, Folder 29)
        - Committee on Legislation
          - Correspondence, summaries of legislation and background information, 1964 (Box 52, Folder 30)
          - Correspondence and memoranda, 1965 (Box 52, Folder 31)
          - Correspondence, memoranda and related material, 1966 (Box 52, Folder 32)
      - Professional Examination Service: correspondence, 1963-1967 (Box 52, Folder 33)
      - Program Area Committee on Medical Care Administration: correspondence and memoranda, 1958-1962 (Box 52, Folder 34)
  - Group Health Association of America
    - Background Papers
      - Association of Labor Health Administrators: correspondence and newsletter, 1956 (Box 53, Folder 35)
      - American Labor Health Association: correspondence and reports, 1958-1959 (Box 53, Folder 36)
      - Cooperative Health Federation of America
        - Correspondence, newsletter and related material, 1953-1954 (Box 53, Folder 37)
        - Correspondence, reports and print material, 1955 (Box 53, Folder 38)
        - Correspondence, reports and resolutions, 1956 (Box 53, Folder 39)
        - Correspondence re: Rural Health Committee, 1956-1957 (Box 53, Folder 40)
        - Correspondence, memoranda and reports, 1957 January-June (Box 53, Folder 41)
      - Group Health Federation of America
        - Correspondence, minutes and reports, 1957 July 17-December (Box 53, Folder 42)
        - Correspondence and reports re: Bylaw Review Committee and Committee on Organization Development, 1957-1958 (Box 53, Folder 43)
        - Correspondence and newsletters, 1958 January-June (Box 53, Folder 44)
        - Correspondence, pamphlets and newsletters, 1958 July-December (Box 53, Folder 45)
        - Correspondence, program material and reports, 1959 January-May (Box 54, Folder 46)
        - Correspondence, articles of incorporation and summary report, 1959 June-December (Box 54, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence and Subject Files
      - Correspondence and notes as president (C.B.E.), 1960 May-June (Box 54, Folder 48)
      - Correspondence as president (C.B.E.), 1960 July-September (Box 54, Folder 49-51)
      - Correspondence as president (C.B.E.), 1960 October-1961 (Box 55, Folder 52-56)
      - Correspondence, general: A - W, 1955-1973 (Box 55, Folder 57)
      - Select
        - American Association of Medical Clinics (Box 55, Folder 57)
          See: box 1, folder 6
        - American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations
          - Correspondence, text (C.B.E.) and reprint, 1964 (Box 55, Folder 58)
          - Correspondence and reports, 1966-1968 (Box 55, Folder 59)
          - U.S.D.H.E.W. grants, 1971-1973 (Box 55, Folder 60)
          - Statements and reports, 1974 (Box 55, Folder 61)
        - American Optometric Association
          - Manuals and reprints, 1959-1963 (Box 55, Folder 62)
          - Correspondence and reports, 1959-1964 (Box 55, Folder 63)
        - Appalachian Regional Hospitals, Inc.
          - Correspondence, pamphlets and print material, 1958-1962 (Box 56, Folder 64)
          - Correspondence, newsclippings and print material, 1963 January-March (Box 56, Folder 65)
          - Survey and Report, 1963 April 21 (Box 56, Folder 66)
          - Correspondence, bylaws, print material and notes, 1963 April-July (Box 56, Folder 67)
          - Correspondence, itineraries and reports, 1963 August-December (Box 56, Folder 68)
          - Correspondence, reports and notes, 1964 (Box 56, Folder 69)
        - Arnett, Thomas M.: correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 56, Folder 70)
        - Arnold, Fortas and Porter: correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 56, Folder 71)
        - Brindle, James: correspondence, 1968 (Box 56, Folder 72)
        - C.B.S. Reports, "Face the Nation": correspondence and text of discussion (Walter Reuther and Edward Annis), 1961 (Box 56, Folder 73)
        - California health plans study: correspondence, guides and print material, 1966 (Box 57, Folder 74)
        - Cleveland plan: correspondence, 1961-1963 (Box 57, Folder 75)
        - Cohelan, Jeffrey: correspondence, 1971 (Box 57, Folder 76)
        - Community Hospital Clinic (Elk City, Oklahoma): correspondence, agreements and budgets, 1962-1963 (Box 57, Folder 77)
        - Coppola, Peter B.: correspondence, 1962-1965 (Box 57, Folder 78)
        - Dearing, W. Palmer
          - Correspondence, 1961 February May (Box 57, Folder 79)
          - Correspondence, reports and text of manuscript, 1962 (Box 57, Folder 80)
          - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 57, Folder 81)
          - Correspondence, A.M.A. source paper and reports, 1964 (Box 57, Folder 82)
          - Correspondence, memoranda and reprints, 1965 (Box 57, Folder 83)
          - Correspondence, testimony and reports re: House bill 2987, 1965 (Box 57, Folder 84)
          - Correspondence, testimony and reports re: King-Anderson amendments to Medicare bill, 1965 (Box 57, Folder 85)
          - Correspondence, memoranda and reprints, 1966 (Box 57, Folder 86)
          - Correspondence, memoranda and reprints, 1967-1972 (Box 57, Folder 87)
        - Developmental Research Project for Social Security Administration: correspondence, minutes and related material, 1965-1966 (Box 57, Folder 88)
        - Farmer's Union Hospital Association: notes and speech draft, undated (Box 58, Folder 89)
        - Federal Employees Health Program: correspondence, statistics and related material, 1959-1964 (Box 58, Folder 90)
        - Filene (Edward A.) Good Will Fund, Inc.: correspondence, agreement and related material, 1960-1964 (Box 58, Folder 91)
        - Fund raising and contributions: correspondence, 1959-1964 (Box 58, Folder 92)